<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A remonstrance of the fight in Legorn-Road between the English and the Dutch, vvith all the passages of the treaty held by the great Duke of Florence before the same. Also many other particulars, as they were presented to his Excellency the Lord General Cromwel, and the Right Honorable the Councel of State.</title>
            <author>Appleton, Henry, fl. 1650-1654.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 86 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75523</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3582</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1068_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210400</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99869204</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99869204</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170623</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75523)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170623)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 248:E1068[5], 159:E1068[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A remonstrance of the fight in Legorn-Road between the English and the Dutch, vvith all the passages of the treaty held by the great Duke of Florence before the same. Also many other particulars, as they were presented to his Excellency the Lord General Cromwel, and the Right Honorable the Councel of State.</title>
                  <author>Appleton, Henry, fl. 1650-1654.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 29, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Field, Printer to the Parliament of England,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing to Henry Appleton, whose name appears on p. 13.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Sep ye 19th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Anglo-Dutch War, 1652-1654 --  Naval operations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  1648-1714 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170623:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A REMONSTRANCE OF THE FIGHT IN LEGORN-ROAD Between the Engliſh and the Dutch, VVith all the Paſſages of the Treaty held by the Great Duke of FLORENCE before the ſame.</p>
            <p>Alſo many other Particulars, as they were preſented to his Excellency the Lord General <hi>CROMWEL,</hi> And the Right Honorable The Councel of State.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Field,</hi> Printer to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>England,</hi> 1653.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:170623:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170623:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To his Excellency the Lord General</hi> CROMWEL, <hi>and the Right Honorable the Councel of State,</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thc humble Remonſtrance of</hi> Henry Appleton, <hi>appointed by the State of</hi> England <hi>to Command the</hi> Leopard, <hi>as alſo the</hi> Bona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture <hi>and</hi> Conſtant Warwick, <hi>for the Convoy of ſeveral Merchant-men through the</hi> Streights.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Having loſt my Journal, it is not poſsible that I ſhould give your Honors ſo particular an Account as I ſhould elſe have done, however, I ſhall not omit any material Paſſage.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>IN the beginning of my Voyage, Captain <hi>Cox</hi> in the <hi>Conſtant Warwick,</hi> contrary to Order, left my Fleet; arriving at <hi>Cales,</hi> I found him with three French Prizes, where he had diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the Priſoners, ſending them to St. <hi>Mary</hi> Port, to the end I might not examine them: the Duke of <hi>Medina-Coeli</hi> hearing of them, orders, they ſhould be put into the Galleys. The Priſoners petitioned me, that they might be free from Slavery: I ſent my Lieutenant and Miniſter to the Duke, who, next day, ſent a Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel of his unto me, and granted me the Priſoners; whom I diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed amongſt our ſhips, and afterwards diſcharged at <hi>Genoa.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Standing for <hi>Genoa,</hi> I diſcovered a great ſhip near the Shore, and to wind-ward of me, that chaſed the <hi>Warwick,</hi> who was ahead and to wind-ward of him; I tacked and ſtood with him, fired a gun to give the <hi>Warwick</hi> notice, but he would not hear: it proved a French-man, who putting out his Colours at the main-top-maſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, tacked and weathered me; I fired many guns at him, ſeveral of the ſhot took place, but ſhe our-ſailed me, not anſwering with one gun. Standing in afterwards for the Port, the <hi>Warwick</hi> meets me with a Letter from our Merchants, which adviſed me of a French-man of War of Thirty ſix guns, that did much hurt upon the Coaſt, and then was as they ſuppoſed in <hi>Savona</hi> Bay: But whereſoever, he was within their Territories, and had no rope made faſt to the Shore; the Republique would be very glad if I could de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy him. This was that very ſhip I chaſed, and had the <hi>Warwick</hi> but aſſiſted me, through the bleſſing of the Lord I ſhould undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly have carried him.</p>
                  <p>Arriving at <hi>Legorn,</hi> the <hi>Warwick</hi> diſcovered a Sail, weighs an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor without my order, and takes a French Sattee coming into the Road. The great Duke demands reſtitution of this Sattee, as being taken in his Port: I called a Conſultation hereupon, but Captain
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170623:3"/> 
                     <hi>Wetheridge</hi> and Captain <hi>Cox</hi> would by no means agree to it, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving me under their hands, that they would anſwer it to your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors. I then returned this Anſwer to his Highneſs, That as the Veſſel was not taken by my Order, ſo I could not reſtore it of my ſelf. Amongſt other Wine the Sattee had in her ſeveral cheſts of Frontignac, and other Preſents for his Highneſs, of which Captain <hi>Cox</hi> ſent me a couple; but I immediately ſent them aſhore to Mr. <hi>Longland</hi> for the Governor, adviſing Captain <hi>Cox,</hi> that he ſhould upon no terms keep away any thing that belonged to the great Dukc. He ſaid, That there was all, and ſo I anſwered the Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. The Duke finding himſelf affronted in his Port, and thus abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the detaining of his Goods, falls into choler with me for the ſame, and charges his Reſident in <hi>England</hi> to lament of me unto your Honors. And I found afterwards, that he had reaſon to be angry, though not with me; for Captain <hi>Cox</hi> kept ſeveral of thoſe Preſents which were ſent the great Duke, and did diſpoſe of them, as he confeſſed to Colonel <hi>Thompſon</hi> here in <hi>London.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>At <hi>Naples</hi> I made Proviſion for my Squadron, and paſſing thence through the Vare of <hi>Meſsina,</hi> I left the <hi>Bonaventure</hi> to bring the ſhip <hi>Agreement</hi> within ſight of <hi>Zant,</hi> and to meet me with the <hi>Mary-Roſe</hi> at <hi>Cyprus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Betwixt <hi>Cerigo</hi> and <hi>Candy,</hi> the <hi>Warwick</hi> takes a French Sattee, and after four or five hours, when he had ranſackt her enough, he lay by the Lee to ſtay for me. In her there was a Chouſe or Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger ſent from the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> to the King of <hi>Tunice,</hi> who had a Paſs from Sir <hi>Thomas Bendiſh,</hi> the which when I read, I uſed what means I could for the reſtoring of his Goods and Cloaths; uſed him with all civility, landed him, as he deſired, on the Iſland of <hi>Candy:</hi> all which he thankfully acknowledged in his Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate which I ſent to Sir <hi>Thomas Bendiſh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Captain <hi>Witheridge</hi> going into <hi>Zant</hi> contrary to Order, the <hi>Mary-Roſe</hi> plies her Voyage for <hi>Cyprus</hi> alone, ſo I ſent the <hi>Warwick</hi> with her; and the <hi>Richard</hi> and <hi>William</hi> for <hi>Scandaroon,</hi> ordering him to come to <hi>Smirna:</hi> upon my arrival at <hi>Smirna,</hi> I found the <hi>Bonaventure</hi> in the Port: ſo ſoon as I had got proviſion for my Fleet, and the Merchants ſhips were ready, I ſet ſail.</p>
                  <p>Being at <hi>Jackamoes Point,</hi> the Conſuls man brings me a Letter from Sir <hi>Thomas Bendiſh;</hi> wherein, in compliance with the Viziers ſolicitation to him, he did deſire I would convoy their Fleet for <hi>Candy,</hi> an Officer of the Viziers being come down on purpoſe, and did expect my anſwer. I wrote a Letter to Sir <hi>Thomas Bendiſh</hi> in excuſe, telling him how much time I had already loſt in waiting for Proviſions in their Port, and what neceſſity there lay upon me to be gone; and withal, how ready I ſhould have been to have done the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> ſervice, as being a Prince in Amity with our Commonwealth, wherein his Deſires and your Honors Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170623:3"/> were not inconſiſtent, but then immediately ſet ſayl, not waiting a reply.</p>
                  <p>Off <hi>Cerigo</hi> the <hi>Warwick</hi> takes a French Sattee, but comes not near me till the next day, when asking for her, he told me ſhe had nothing in her, but a little Money (bringing almoſt Two hundred Chickeens of Gold) and empty Cask, ſo of himſelf he gave her to the French again.</p>
                  <p>At <hi>Zant</hi> I met with Captain <hi>Badily</hi> going for <hi>Scanderoone,</hi> I left the <hi>Warwick</hi> to convoy the ſhips that were almoſt laden in that Port, to <hi>Melſina,</hi> whether they came as I was going out of the <hi>Vare,</hi> they and the <hi>Phenix</hi> in their company, never acquainting me with their intentions or bidding me farewel, ſtood away for <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Having received ſeveral Letters from the Merchants at <hi>Naples,</hi> that a great quantity of Silk lay ready, waiting for our coming, ſending the <hi>Benaventure</hi> with the <hi>Mary</hi> to <hi>Legorn,</hi> to the end that ſhe, the <hi>Victory</hi> at <hi>Genoa,</hi> and any other ſhips bound homewards, might be in a readineſs when I ſhould call, I went into <hi>Naples.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Between this place and <hi>Legorn</hi> a Meſſenger from Mr. <hi>Longland</hi> brings a Letter to me, wherein was intimated the Hoſtility the Dutch had offered to our Ships in our own Seas, whileſt their Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors were in treaty with us.</p>
                  <p>Coming to <hi>Legorn</hi> he brought me your Honors Letter, wherein you Ordered me to conſult with him what was beſt to do; Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly I did, and he then gave it me under his hand, That it was ſafeſt to ſtay in that Port till the next Poſt came: Before that time Fourteen Sayl of the Dutch came into the Road; ſo ſoon as I eſpyed them, I put to Sea with the <hi>Bonaventure</hi> and the four Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants ſhips, and towed the <hi>Leopard</hi> through the Fleet, there being no Winde at all, expecting the Engaging; but ſeeing they came to Anchor in a friendly maner, I towed a ſecond time amongſt them, and then anchored betwixt them and the Shore, our Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants ſhips being betwixt me and the Shore: while they were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſayl and I cloſe by, their Admiral fired Nine Guns without ſhot, being perſwaded by my Officers, it was a Salute to me, I anſwered him with Nine ſhotted, not having any drawn; but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards he made that paſs for a Salute to the Port. Underſtanding that the Difference grew higher, it was agreed on by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders and the Merchants, to unlade all fine Goods; but this the Dutch forbad, however through the aſſiſtance of the Governor, we landed what we pleaſed.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Warwick</hi> having carreen'd at <hi>Genoa,</hi> I ſent her by the advice of Mr. <hi>Longland,</hi> to finde out Captain <hi>Badily,</hi> and to acquaint him with the Breach with <hi>Holland;</hi> the Dutch ſaying, <hi>That at that time they had received Order to fight us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Dutch had ſent ſeveral times to <hi>Florence,</hi> to ſollicit the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170623:4"/> Duke to deny Protection to our ſhips, and gave high words, That they had Orders from their Maſters to ſink or burn us in the Road; Hereupon the Governors ſent to Mr. <hi>Longland</hi> to acquaint me, That if I expected Protection from the Duke, I muſt come into the <hi>Mould,</hi> or elſe they would not fire a Gun in my favor; ſo Mr. <hi>Longland</hi> being aboard at a Conſultation, it was agreed we ſhould come into the <hi>Mould,</hi> and ſo we did.</p>
                  <p>Some few days after, the Colonel of the Town ſent Mr. <hi>Long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to acquaint me with theſe Propoſitions the Dutch had made unto his Highneſs; <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That no Man of War having an opportunity to depart, ought by a moſt ancient Law, to ſtay in any Port beyond ſuch a time. That they, to that end the Engliſh might go to Sea, had ſtaid out ſeveral days: That they would give the Merchants ſhips leave to relade their Goods, give them free liberty to depart; nor would they ſtir till they had been departed five days, the which if not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, they would forbear endeavoring to ruine them no longer. To theſe I was immediately to give my Anſwer: The opinion of our Factory then preſent, was, That whereas the Dutch had waited ſeveral times upon the Duke, and did ſollicit daily that he would deny Protection to the Engliſh, and all this while the Engliſh never owned him, nor went to give him thanks (as I indeed deſired, but Mr. <hi>Longland</hi> oppoſed me in it.) The Duke now ſeemed to ſpoil the vertue of our Gratitude, by his neceſſitating us unto it; ſo Mr. <hi>Longland</hi> did deſire me to ſend one to treat with the Duke accordingly: That himſelf with other Merchants would go to thank him for his Protection of their Goods, and that the Maſters would do the ſame for the protection of their ſhips, and joyntly to beſeech him the continuance of his Favors; Hereupon Mr. <hi>Long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and my ſelf, with ſeveral of the Merchants, deſired Mr. <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaniel Reading</hi> to undertake the Buſineſs, the which he did at our entreaty; and at that time ingaged himſelf on my behalf, That I ſhould not diſturb his Highneſs Port, except I were commanded to the contrary; How he managed the ſame, and effected the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of our Protection, your Honors have underſtood by his own Relation; the Lord having at that time viſited me with a violent and tedious Sickneſs, ſo that I could not write; during the time of my ſickneſs, there came News to <hi>Legorn</hi> of Captain <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dileys</hi> being engaged with the Dutch of <hi>Monte Chriſto;</hi> hereupon, although I was not able to walk alone, and Captain <hi>Wetheridge</hi> was juſt dead, I reſolved to go to help him, notwithſtanding there lay ſix Dutch Men of War in the Road; but as I was got aboard and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to go out, I received a Letter from Captain <hi>Badiley</hi> of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>Porta Longone,</hi> and deſiring me not to think of ſtirring till he was fit to put to ſea.</p>
                  <p>I ſent for Captain <hi>Cox</hi> to command the <hi>Bonaventure,</hi> and when
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170623:4"/> he came, the <hi>Phenix</hi> which was taken by the Dutch, was brought into the <hi>Mould,</hi> and he was always talking of burning her; I ſent him in particular that Order which your Honors ſent me for not diſturbing the Great Duke's Port, told him the Engagement I had lately made to the contrary, and the great danger all our ſhips were in, if he ſhould burn the <hi>Phenix,</hi> not onely for the incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the Duke and Dutch againſt us, but alſo of the firing of our own ſhips too; however he perſiſted in his actings, contrary to your Honors and my Order, chaſing their Boats, and occaſioning many complaints of the Dutch unto the Governor: I told him how much I had ſuffered for his former Inſolencies in this place, how what he did might tend to the ruine of us all; but yet he would not hear me, acting ſeveral times againſt my Order, ſtirring up his men by many ſeditious ſpeeches againſt me, and never own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me at all, notwithſtanding the Commiſſion I had from your Honors, and the many reſpects and continual courteſies which I had always ſhewn him, ſo that I was neceſſitated to bid him return to his former command, leaſt he ſhould make a Mutiny amongſt our ſhips; In the interim Captain <hi>Badiley</hi> arrives and brings me Order for his Commanding in Chief, the which I readily obeyed.</p>
                  <p>Captain <hi>Badiley</hi> now placeth Captain <hi>Cox</hi> in the <hi>Bonaventure:</hi> and I being freed of the Engagement which I had made unto the Duke, it was agreed on to ſurprize the <hi>Phenix</hi> then in the Road, riding the outermoſt ſhip, with the Engliſh Colours under theirs.</p>
                  <p>The Attempt was thus:</p>
                  <p>Captain <hi>Cox</hi> in the <hi>Elizabeth's</hi> Shallop with nine Oars and four Sitters, my Lieutenant <hi>Yong</hi> in the <hi>Sampſon</hi>'s Pinnace, with thirty four men, and Lieutenant <hi>Symmes</hi> in the <hi>Bonaventure</hi>'s Pinnace with thirty four more.</p>
                  <p>Having loſt one another ſeveral times, at laſt towards morning they all met, and coming up in the <hi>Phenix</hi> ſtern, Captain <hi>Cox</hi> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered them to board the ſhip on both ſides, whileſt he went for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward with his Shallop to cut the Cabel; the Lieutenants and their crew entred, and after ſome diſpute, in which Lieutenant <hi>Yong</hi> and two more were ſlain, they took the ſhip; Young <hi>Tromp</hi> and ſome of his Officers eſcaped in their own Boat; the ſhip being under ſayl, and the Fight over, up comes Captain <hi>Cox,</hi> drives the men out of the Cabbin which had done the ſervice, and after found the Money, ſaying, <hi>The Cabbin belonged unto him;</hi> and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Promiſe made before the Enterprize, to ſhare the Booty equally, he kept it to his private uſe; all which, ſeveral of the men are ready to make good by Oath.</p>
                  <p>In the morning I ſent Mr. <hi>Longland</hi> an accompt of the particulars, to the end your Honors might have notice quickly of the ſame; and he immediately ſends his ſervant with the news, not giving me the liberty of ſending by him.</p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:170623:5"/>
                  <p> About this time a Dutch man came aboard my ſhip, whom I ſuſpected for a Spy, with Mr. <hi>Longland</hi>'s advice I clapt him in the Bilboes; having leave to eaſe himſelf in the ſhips-head, he leaps into the water, and ſwimming to the <hi>Moulde,</hi> two of my men being a ſhore, I bad them ſtop him; but he promiſing the Centinel mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to reſcue him, got to his houſe. I went aſhore, deſiring the Sentinel to deliver me my Priſoner, promiſing, I would carry him to the Governor. This he granted, and carrying him aboard, there came a Sergeant and two Soldiers, demanding of the Priſoner, threatning to fire at me elſe: The Priſoner leaps out of my Boat, and went aſhore. I ſent my Miniſter to Mr. <hi>Longland,</hi> to let him know punctually what had paſt, to the end, he might acquaint the Governor therewith; but Mr. <hi>Longland</hi> would not take the pains, whereby the Duke and his Miniſters, through miſinformation from the Dutch, were much incenſed againſt me.</p>
                  <p>And theſe, I do aſſure your Honors, are all the Circumſtances of that Buſineſs, as many now in Town are ready to depoſe.</p>
                  <p>Two days after, Mr. <hi>Longland</hi> comes aboard me with one of the Dukes Captains, telling me, the Duke would ſpeak with me at <hi>Piſa;</hi> I asked him, what he thought it was about, he anſwered, that he could not tell, but he would go along with me. Being up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the way, he asked me what I would ſay to the Duke, in caſe he ſhould ask me about the taking of the <hi>Phenix?</hi> I ſaid, That I could eaſily clear my ſelf of the former Engagement I had made unto him, for it was conditional, if I were not commanded to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, as here I was by Captain <hi>Badily,</hi> who poſitively did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, to retake or deſtroy the Frigot; and to that end, ſent ſeveral men from <hi>Port-Langone,</hi> promiſing to each of them a good ſum of money. Mr. <hi>Longland</hi> perceiving that I could clear my ſelf from breaking my Engagement with the Duke, and that the Dukes diſpleaſure muſt light on Captain <hi>Badily</hi> and himſelf, upon our ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rival at <hi>Piſa,</hi> goes to <hi>Signior Pandolfino,</hi> the Dukes Secretary of War, and having had private conference with him, I then was ſent for to the Palace; but <hi>Pandolfino</hi> would not ſuffer me to ſee the Duke, commanding the Governor of the Caſtle to put me in a coach and carry me away to the Caſtle; Mr. <hi>Longland</hi> and Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Wood</hi> (of whom I never did deſerve but well) publiquely tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphed, that they had brought me into that condition. And not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding they pretended kindneſs in their going with me, it ſeemed, it onely was to work their ends upon me; for during my four days impriſonment in the Caſtle, they, not onely came not near me themſelves, but none elſe were ſuffered to come that would; denying to let my men know what became of me, or where I was, that they might ſend me Cloathes. At laſt, an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer being come from Captain <hi>Badily,</hi> That he would do Juſtice upon any under his command, that ſhould commit ſo high Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170623:5"/> againſt the Duke, as was pretended I had done; I was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed by a party of his Horſe, through woods and by ways, Forty miles, unto St. <hi>Vincents,</hi> where for three nights together I lay up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſtones; and thence being carried by a <hi>Faluca</hi> to Port <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rara,</hi> there I remained till Captain <hi>Badily</hi> did ſend to fetch me.</p>
                  <p>Nor did Mr. <hi>Longland</hi> think he had yet triumphed enough over me, till as he had made me ſuffer much in my Perſon abroad, ſo I ſhould more in my Reputation at home; and therefore he conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues to have a Currier ſent on purpoſe, to complain unto your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors of my violating our Nations Faith, and the Dukes Port, in ſurprizing of the Frigot, and affronting of his Centinel: whereas Mr. <hi>Longland</hi> well knew, as God and the world doth, Captain <hi>Badily</hi> commanded the taking of the Frigot, and takes it upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and that I never touched the Centinel or gave him an ill word; and could I have obtained the liberty of ſpeaking unto the Duke, as afterwards he told me, all this had been prevented.</p>
                  <p>The Dukes Currier returning, your Honors ſent me an Order to command me home, and that I ſhould make all the haſte as poſſibly I could over land; I obeyed it with all readineſs, and to that end, coming to <hi>Legorn,</hi> where the Dukes Secretary, Captain <hi>Badily,</hi> and the Dutch, were in a Treaty; and having there concluded to fight the Dutch, it was ordered by a Councel of War, That I ſhould ſtay to command the <hi>Leopard</hi> till the Fight was over, Provided I would give ſix hundred Crowns to have leave from the Duke; and Captain <hi>Badily</hi> would then Anſwer to your Honors for my not co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming home by Land, according to your Order.</p>
                  <p>I anſwered him, That though no man on earth ſhould be more ready to ſerve his Countrey then my ſelf, that yet to buy the hazard of my Life at ſuch a price, were to invite a Curſe from my Wife and Children, whom I have too much wronged already by my ſerving of the State; that therefore, though I would ſerve them, though I got no money by it, yet I would not give money for to ſerve them.</p>
                  <p>And truly when I conſidered it, I found it a bad bargain, for if through that Compoſition I ſhould be admitted to venture my Life, and through the Mercy of the Lord I ſhould out live the Fight, that yet I muſt when all was done, hold on my journey over Land.</p>
                  <p>While this was in diſpute, there came an Expreſs from his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to his Secretary, ſignifying, That he was not onely contented, but much deſired I ſhould be admitted to my former Command.</p>
                  <p>So I was ſetled in the <hi>Leopard,</hi> and Captain <hi>Badily</hi> having ſent ſeveral Expreſſes to Captain <hi>Cox,</hi> to come with the other ſhips he then commanded, from <hi>Naples</hi> to Port <hi>Longone:</hi> He contrary to all Order goes to the Vare of <hi>Meſina,</hi> but after more then Twenty days expecting him, at laſt he comes, leaving the <hi>Henry Bona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture</hi>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:170623:6"/> behinde him. Whereupon, Captain <hi>Badily</hi> ſeeing Captain <hi>Cox</hi> had acted ſo much againſt his Orders alſo, and that he had oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned the omiſſion of ſo many opportunities to get out and joyn, the Enemy not being ſometimes but Five, other times Two, and after none at all in Port <hi>Longone,</hi> their Admiral being caſt away, and another of their ſhips faſt upon the Rocks; and laſtly, having come away without the <hi>Henry Bonaventure,</hi> which Veſſel might have done good ſervice in the Ingagement, and could do none in waiting where he was, his Prize being in a ſafe Port, he told me, That the State had better to have given Twenty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pounds, rather then Captain <hi>Cox</hi> ſhould have carried himſelf in that maner; and ſince we hear, the Dutch have taken her.</p>
                  <p>Captain <hi>Badily</hi> departs for the fitting his Eight ſhips and a Fire ſhip at Port <hi>Ferara,</hi> and being under ſail, ſends me Orders to haſte to him, ſo ſoon as the Dutch weighed Anchor to go towards him; and to the end he might not be over-powered by the Dutch before I could aſſiſt, commands me for to haſte upon my Life, and that with all the ſail that I could make.</p>
                  <p>Captain <hi>Badily</hi> plying near the <hi>Malhora,</hi> ſends his Lieutenant to me in the night, to know our readineſs, and to adviſe, that the <hi>Warrick</hi> ſhould be ready near the <hi>Mould-head</hi> by break of day, to keep off the Enemies Fire ſhip, which, with Twenty five more, lay ready with their Top-ſails looſe in the tops, and their Anchors a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peek, ready to wait our motion. I called a Conſultation upon his coming, and at that time there ſpringing a ſmall Gale, had ſome thoughts of getting out; but Mr. <hi>Longland</hi> not being there, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out whom we durſt not act, and Captain <hi>Badily</hi>'s Order being to the contrary; and during this Conſultation the Gale ended, and there was no Wind ſtirring, it was agreed on not to ſtir till morning.</p>
                  <p>In the morning Mr. <hi>Longland</hi> comes aboard, and then I told him what we reſolved upon in the night, he much approved thereof, for had we ſtirred, it falling calm, we had in probability been ruined. Captain <hi>Badily</hi> keeps ſtill near the <hi>Malhora,</hi> the <hi>Phenix Warwick,</hi> and another of our ſhips come to the ſouth-ward of the <hi>Lanthorn,</hi> and Captain <hi>Badily</hi> ſtood after them, hereupon the Dutch weighed.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Longland</hi> and the Commiſſioners being all aboard me, concluded we ſhould make all poſſible haſte, the Winde being Eaſterly off Shore, my Orders being to haſten as for Life, Mr. <hi>Longland</hi> and all the Commanders agreeing we ſhould looſe no more time, we ſlipt our Cables, and made all the ſail we could. The Dutch were now in the middle betwixt Captain <hi>Badily</hi> and our ſhips. By that time our ſtermoſt ſhip was well cleared off the <hi>Mould,</hi> the Dutch tacked upon us, we ſtood with them reſolving to break through, they fired at us; (the wind now changeth to South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſt)
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170623:6"/> ſo that Captain <hi>Badily</hi> and his Fleet could have come quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-wind up to us.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Bonaventure</hi> had not fired twenty Guns, when within three of her lengths from the <hi>Leopard,</hi> ſhe blew up in the Air; while I was clearing my ſelf off the wrack, the <hi>Sun</hi> of forty Guns, and the <hi>Julius Ceſar</hi> of thirty eight, boarded me both of the Lard-board ſide.</p>
                  <p>Captain <hi>Seaman</hi> in the <hi>Sampſon</hi> coming to my Aſſiſtance, as was agreed, was boarded by yong <hi>Tromp</hi> in a ſhip of forty two Guns; <hi>Tromp</hi> ſeeing himſelf worſted by him, calls to the Fire ſhip, who boarded the <hi>Sampſon</hi> on the other ſide, and fired her immediately.</p>
                  <p>Captain <hi>Marſh</hi> in the <hi>Levant-Merchant</hi> was boarded by a ſhip of thirty ſix Guns.</p>
                  <p>Captain <hi>Wood</hi> in the <hi>Peregrine</hi> alſo by another, but Captain <hi>Fiſher</hi> in the <hi>Mary</hi> made his way through the Fleet, and joyned with Captain <hi>Badily.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This was the condition of my Squadron all of us, eſpecially my ſelf having the ſeveral Broad<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>ſides from the Enemies other ſhips paſſed upon us, whileſt we were diſputing with theſe that boarded us.</p>
                  <p>All this while Captain <hi>Badily</hi> and his Fleet lay awether of us, making ſeveral ſhot, though at too great a diſtance, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Wind was very good for his coming up.</p>
                  <p>Captain <hi>Cox</hi> runs the <hi>Phenix</hi> aground the Main, and there lyes for half an hour.</p>
                  <p>Captain <hi>Ell</hi> in the <hi>Lewis</hi> comes up to my Aſſiſtance, firing at them that poured their Broad-ſides on me, as alſo on them that boarded me.</p>
                  <p>Captain <hi>Fiſher</hi> in the <hi>Mary</hi> making his way through the Enemy a ſecond time, did very good ſervice.</p>
                  <p>Captain <hi>Badily</hi> at laſt comes within half ſhot of me, betwixt the <hi>Leopard</hi> and the ſhore, and he with others of his Fleet did make ſome ſhot.</p>
                  <p>Captain <hi>Wood</hi> not being relieved in ſo long time, ſurrenders.</p>
                  <p>Captain <hi>Marſh</hi> having ſunk the great ſhip that boarded him, immediately was boarded by another, and being over-powred by the Enemy, much torn, many of his men ſlain, and none of our friends coming to relieve him, was taken.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Warwick</hi> coming up the ſecond time, and giving ſeveral Broad-ſides to them that boarded me, my ſelf, the Maſter, and the Corporal called to him to forbear firing at thoſe two that boarded me, they having called for Quarter, and to engage with them that plyed their Broad-ſides on me.</p>
                  <p>Captain <hi>Badily</hi> orders Captain <hi>Whiteing</hi> in our Fire-ſhip to board the Dutch Admiral, promiſing that himſelf would engage him, till he had made his Graplings faſt; accordingly he makes
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170623:7"/> towards him, but Captain <hi>Badily</hi> not coming up as he expected, by which means the Dutch Admiral played all his Guns upon him, was ſunk juſt at his ſtern.</p>
                  <p>I ſtill expecting that Captain <hi>Badily</hi> and the Frigots would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage thoſe five ſhips that gauled me in that maner, to the end I might have taken poſſeſſion of thoſe two ſhips which had ſo long boarded me, and called for Quarter, and for a good while forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed firing; but the Lord of Heaven having otherwiſe determined it, they not onely refuſed to help me themſelves, but would not let others do it that would; for Captain <hi>Ell</hi> who lay near me, and did great Execution on the Enemy, coming to lye at my Star<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board-bowe for my Aſſiſtance, was called away by Captain <hi>Badily,</hi> who without any more ado ſet his Main-ſayl, and made way from me with all ſpeed he could; ſo Captain <hi>Ell</hi> and Captain <hi>Fiſher,</hi> who once more was coming up for to help me, and was the inner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt and northermoſt ſhip of all, ſeeing Captain <hi>Badily</hi> to leave me thus, were neceſſitated for their own ſafety to follow after.</p>
                  <p>The Dutch ſeeing Captain <hi>Badily</hi> thus gone, chaſed his nine Sayl with eight, of which, the <hi>Admiral,</hi> the <hi>Redhare,</hi> and the <hi>Half-Moon,</hi> all diſabled ſhips, were three: And ſeeing I was thus aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned, up comes the Vice-Admiral of the Dutch with five ſhips more, and fires at me with more violence; and thoſe two ſhips that had cryed Quarrer ſeeing me left alone, began again to fire: And after two hours diſpute, their Vice Admiral laid me croſs the ſtern, raking me fore and after: our ſtern being beaten in, and Til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler ſhot in pieces, fourteen Guns made unſerviceable, the ſhip every way pitifully torn, almoſt half of our men diſabled, and my ſelf, Lieutenant, and many Officers wounded, and the Enemy increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; but moſt of all, my men being diſcouraged by their friends forſaking of them, they reſolved to fight no longer; I forced them ſeveral times into their Quarters, and trying fair means as well as fowl, proffered a hundred Crowns for every ſhot that they would make out of a Demy-canon in the Gun room: The Gunner and one of the Maſters mates made two ſhots, and were making more, but preſently I underſtood how ſome did call for Quarter, ſaying, the Enemy was on the Poope; hereupon I called the Gunner, and privately bade him blow the Poope up, as he was going to blow it up, and aſſiſted by the Maſter and Corporal therein, the men per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it, and laid hands on him, I came ſtraight to reſcue him, but then they ſeized on me, putting my ſhoulder out of joynt, by wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting my weapons from me, and held me, whileſt ſome of them called for Quarter, until I was delivered into the Enemies hands, who, had not my men intreated for me, had reſolved to kill me, for I denyed Quarter.</p>
                  <p>Being thus their Priſoner, I was conveyed aboard their Vice-Admiral, and after their heat was over, they uſed me civilly and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170623:7"/> dreſſed my wounds; confeſſing to me ſeveral times, That if Captain <hi>Badily</hi> had aſſiſted me with his Fleet, they ſhould not have been able to withſtand us.</p>
                  <p>The next day after the Fight they cleared all the Priſoners, except Captain <hi>Seaman,</hi> Captain <hi>Marſh</hi> and my ſelf.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Longland</hi> ſends thoſe that would go upon his tearms to <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice,</hi> but he not giving them but two Dollars and a half to carry them ſo many days Journey through a ſtrange Country, many refuſed to go, knowing that twice as much could not defray their charges: Some that undertook to go, dyed by the way of Famine; and they that did arrive were almoſt naked, having ſold their cloaths for victuals.</p>
                  <p>And during our nine weeks Impriſonment, although we always were within a mile of the Town, Mr. <hi>Longland</hi> never was the man that owned us, or ſent to help us in our wants; of which the Dutch themſelves complained.</p>
                  <p>Upon our ſeveral Securities to appear in <hi>Holland,</hi> they gave us leave to go, and being come aſhoar, the Great Duke ſent to ſpeak with me; accordingly I waited on him, and there he pleaſed to tell me, That he was ſorry for my ſufferings, but knew no way to make me amends but by his Letter to the Parliament.</p>
                  <p>What elſe his Highneſs and ſeveral about him, what Mr. <hi>Long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> own people, and the <hi>Italians</hi> which were Spectators ſaid of this Engagement, I ſhall forbear to mention as I do many other things; the concealing whereof, ſhould not more prejudice your Honors or my ſelf, then the relating them can poſſibly reflect on them whom they concern.</p>
                  <p>This I ſhall onely ſay, That whereas Mr. <hi>Longland</hi> chargeth me with breaking Orders in coming out to ſoon, I ſhall refer your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors to the Premiſes; to Captain <hi>Badily</hi>'s Letters, which I have to ſhew, and to the Oaths now ready to be made herein, to judge, aſſuring you, That when he and the Commanders had unanimouſly agreed to our going out, and himſelf had taken his leave and was going in his Boat aſhoar, he returned, and prayed us to haſte for fear that Captain <hi>Badily</hi> ſhould be oppreſſed before we came.</p>
                  <p>The ſeveral Accompts of moneys I received, disburſed or char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged upon the State through the Voyage, are all in readineſs when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever that your Honors ſhall appoint to Audit them.</p>
                  <p>To give your Honors no further trouble, This is the ſum of what hath happened ſince my going out, the truth whereof, as in his preſence who is Searcher of all hearts, I do aver; nor hath my naming any particular in this Narative proceeded from ſpleen to him, but love to truth, to the end your Honors might be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partially informed how your Affairs were managed, rendring
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170623:8"/> moſt humble thanks for my Exchange: I ſubmit my ſelf to your conſideration, as of what I have done, ſo of what I have ſuffered for you.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Henry Appleton.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>The <hi>Sampſon</hi> was fired after an hour and a halfs diſpute.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Peregrine</hi> was ſurrendred within three hours.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Levant</hi> Merchant held out four.</p>
                  <p>And the <hi>Leopard,</hi> in all, above ſix hours.</p>
                  <p>In <hi>Legorn</hi> we received as much reſpect and civility from his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs <hi>The great Duke,</hi> as from any Prince into whoſe Port we came: And as to my own particular, notwithſtanding the means uſed to to incenſe him againſt me, yet he commanded, while I was in his hands, that I ſhould want for nothing; ſo that both in the Caſtle of <hi>Piſa</hi> and <hi>Porta Ferara,</hi> alſo I was treated with all kindneſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Edmond Seaman <hi>Captain of the</hi> Sampſon, <hi>having been with Captain</hi> Appleton, <hi>From his coming into</hi> Smyrna <hi>till his return into</hi> England <hi>(except the time of his firſt Impriſonment) and having peruſed the Narrative he hath made; foraſmuch as I was preſent at, and privy to moſt of the Tranſactions therein, do aver the truth thereof, and am ready to maintain the ſame by Oath, when ever I ſhall be called thereunto: And in teſtimony thereof, do hereto ſet my Hand.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Edmond Seaman.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>I <hi>Stephen Marſh,</hi> Captain of the <hi>Levant</hi> Merchant, having per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſed this Narration, do finde it, for ſo much as I was capable of knowing in the whole Voyage, eſpecially in the Engagement (being in my own Veſſel) to be true; The Premiſes I am ready to make good upon Oath, whenever called: And in teſtimony thereof, do hereto ſet my hand.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Stephen Marſh.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>I <hi>William Ell</hi> Captain of the <hi>Lewis,</hi> do certifie, That as I was going to relieve Captain <hi>Appleton,</hi> being fully reſolved either to lay him aboard, or elſe the Enemies that lay on board him; my men cryed out, They would loſe their lives rather then let their Vice-Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral be ruined: Captain <hi>Badily</hi> with his own mouth calls me away, told me I muſt ſtand after him; and though he had fair opportunity to Engage the Enemies Admiral ſingle, yet did he not do the ſame: And having peruſed this Narration of Captain <hi>Appletons,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring it with my own Journal, I finde it (for ſo much as I was capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of knowing in my own Veſſel) to be true; The Premiſes I am ready to make good upon Oath, when ever called: In teſtimony thereof, I do ſet to my hand.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>William Ell.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:170623:8"/>
                  <p>We whoſe Names are here under-written, do teſtifie, That Captain <hi>Peter Whiteing</hi> Commander of the Fire-ſhip, after the ſinking of his ſhip, and his coming aboard Captain <hi>Badily,</hi> did in our hearing ſeveral times ſay, That Captain <hi>Badily,</hi> having left Captain <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleton</hi> in the middle of his Enemies, two hours after ſeeing from his Poop, that the <hi>Leopards</hi> Colours were ſtill in the Fore-top, and the Guns firing, fell, as he had good reaſon, into paſsion, ſaying, He was an undone man for ever.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Robert Daines. Samuel Wily.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>We whoſe Names are hereunto written, do teſtifie, That the Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians and French in <hi>Legorn</hi> ſeeing how Captain <hi>Appleton</hi> behaved himſelf towards the Dutch, and how Captain <hi>Badily</hi> behaved him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf towards Captain <hi>Appleton,</hi> and the other ſhips, proteſted, They would tear Captain <hi>Badily</hi> in pieces for a coward as he was, if ever he ſhould come on ſhore.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Robert Daines. Samuel Wily.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>If your Excellency ſhall not conceive theſe Teſtimonies enough to make out the truth of my Remonſtrance, I ſhall, when ever cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led unto it, produce very many more: as alſo ſhall readily Anſwer to any thing thing that can be objected againſt me.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Hen: Appilton.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Declaration of</hi> Edmund Seaman <hi>Commander of the</hi> Samſon</head>
               <opener>Humbly ſheweth,</opener>
               <p>THat being at <hi>Smirna,</hi> Captain <hi>Appleton</hi> came into the Port, where I ſhall briefly give you an account of our Proceedings. Off of <hi>Livorn</hi> ſome five or ſix Leagues, we had a Filvea met us, and gave us notice of the Affront the Dutch gave our Nation, whereupon, we much deſired to be gone for <hi>England,</hi> but Mr. <hi>Longland</hi> deſired Captain <hi>Appleton</hi> to ſtay till the next Poſt; and in the interim, Four ſail of the Dutch ſhips of War came in upon us, but before they came into the Road, we all weighed and ſtood to them, ſo we and they anchored; we anchored between them and the ſhore, and there were blockt up by them. Soon after, Mr. <hi>Longland</hi> came aboard, and told us, That he was ſent by the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor and Collonel of the Town, that we muſt come into the <hi>Mould,</hi> for where we rid we could not be ſecure from our Enemy; ſo that night we got all our ſhips into the <hi>Mould,</hi> but were forced firſt to lighten them: ſo there we were in ſafety, we having the Grand Dukes Protection. So within two days of our being in the <hi>Mould,</hi> it was agreed upon by Mr. <hi>Longland</hi> and Captain <hi>Apple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> and the reſt of the Nation, That ſome ſhould go up to <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:170623:9"/> to give the Grand Duke Thanks for his protecting of us; whereupon it was agreed, That Mr. <hi>Longland,</hi> Mr. <hi>Boneile,</hi> Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Roop,</hi> Captain <hi>Wood</hi> and my ſelf, in the behalf of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, and Mr. <hi>Reading</hi> at the requeſt of the Nation, for Captain <hi>Appleton</hi> being very ſick at that time. We no ſooner were arrived at <hi>Florence,</hi> but we were preſently ſent for to come to the Grand Duke, which we did; and as ſoon as we had given him Thanks for his protecting of us, he asked us, If we thought our ſelves ſecure from the Dutch? I anſwered him, That the Dutch we did not fear ſo long as he was our friend. Soon after we had news, that Captain <hi>Badily</hi> was engaged with the Dutch, and then there lay in the Road four of their men of War, and two that they had taken up in their ſervice, ſo that there were never leſs then ſix of them in the Road of <hi>Livorn.</hi> Captain <hi>Badily</hi> being come ſafe to <hi>Porta Longona,</hi> ſent Captain <hi>Cox</hi> to ſee what condition the ſhips were in at <hi>Livorn,</hi> and to have the Merchant ſhips go out to engage with the Dutch; I anſwered him, I would not act any thing without a Warrant, either from the States or from my Owners: which ſoon after, Captain <hi>Badily</hi> or Mr. <hi>Longland</hi> ſent to the States for Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions, to take up our ſhips, which, as ſoon as we received the ſaid Commiſſions, obeyed them, and fitted our ſhips for men of War. Captain <hi>Badily</hi> being at <hi>Livorn,</hi> coming aboard the <hi>Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pard</hi> in the afternoon, calling a Councel of War; and when we were all together, he was pleaſed to tell us, That we muſt deliver the <hi>Phenix</hi> or the <hi>Bonaventure,</hi> or be gone out of the <hi>Mould:</hi> Notwithſtanding, how much it concerned us to know what was treated on by the Dukes Orders, he to that end ſending his Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary from <hi>Florence,</hi> to accommodate the Difference between the Dutch and us: Captain <hi>Badily</hi> never acquainted us with any thing but a neceſſity of delivering up the <hi>Bonaventure</hi> or <hi>Phenix,</hi> or elſe be gone in Fifteen days. Whether we might not have ſtayed upon other Terms, I cannot ſpeak to, Captain <hi>Badily</hi> and Mr. <hi>Longland</hi> doing all without acquainting us further. This onely I am ſure that the Secretary ſaid, That if Fifteen days were not enough, we might have Ten, and after that Ten days more: whereupon Mr. <hi>Longland</hi> ſaid, That the Grand Duke carried himſelf with as much reſpect to our Nation as can be, not forcing us out of his Port, but endeavoring what he could to compoſe our ſtay; and notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding we might have had ſo much time, whereby we might have been in a better condition to fight, or elſe might have received Orders from the State, what to have done therein. But after ſome diſpute we agreed, That he ſhould get the reſt of the ſhips ready that were in <hi>Porta Longona,</hi> and then ſee what might be done: when we were all ready, having fitted our ſhips for ſailing and fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, we looked every hour for Captain <hi>Badily,</hi> which on the ſecond of <hi>March,</hi> we eſpied our Fleet at the going down of the Sun,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170623:9"/> which was a great encouraging of our men; that night Captain <hi>Cox</hi> came aboard the <hi>Leopard,</hi> and from Captain <hi>Badily,</hi> to deſire us to be ready at an hours warning, which we obeyed. On Thurſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day night Captain <hi>Upcher</hi> and Captain <hi>Whiting</hi> came and told us, that they were cloſe by the Lanthorn, but as ſoon as it was day, we found no ſuch thing, but were altogether, three or four Leagues off by judgement. After that they were gone, Captain <hi>Badily</hi> ſent his Lieutenant to us, that if in caſe the wind ſhould come off ſhore, that we ſhould come out upon our lives, before he was too much engaged; which he, for his part, as far as I could ſee, did never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to do: And on Friday morning we received order to come out with all ſpeed, and that morning, Mr. <hi>Longland</hi> with the reſt of the Captains reſolved to go with one general conſent; the Dutch being all weighed and ſtood to Captain <hi>Badily,</hi> ſo that it was Mr. <hi>Longland</hi>'s deſire, that we ſhould make all the haſte that poſſible we could, before our Admiral was too much engaged, and ſo took his leave and went aſhore from us; and we having a fine Breaſe off the ſhore, immediately ſet ſail, the <hi>Bonaventure</hi> firſt, the <hi>Leopard</hi> next, and after all the reſt. But we no ſooner were all clear of the <hi>Mould-head,</hi> but Captain <hi>Badily</hi> ſtood off; the Dutch ſeeing that, bore in upon us, and in leſs then half an hour that we were come out, we were engaged; and in the interim, of a ſudden, the Wind ſhifted to the South-Eaſt and South-Eaſt by South. Captain <hi>Badily</hi> and his Fleet, if he had pleaſed, might have been as near the Dutch as we were. The <hi>Bonaventure</hi> in a ſhort time blew up; and then we looking for Captain <hi>Badily</hi> and his Fleet to have fallen on, could have no Relief of him: but inſtead of coming to relieve us, chaſed one of the ſhips belonging to <hi>Livorn,</hi> though he ſaw the Dukes Colours flying; and as ſoon as Captain <hi>Cox</hi> made him coming back, ran his Frigot aground upon the Weather ſhore, ſo that we had but little Relief all this time. At length I was boarded by a ſhip of 20 Guns for above an hour and a half, and at laſt boarded on the other ſide by a Fire-ſhip, and ſo we were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed; all this time no Relief from Captain <hi>Badily,</hi> nor none of his ſquadron, though he might, if he had pleaſed, have been in the midſt of us, had he not ſtood off when we came firſt out of the <hi>Mould,</hi> and ſo he ſaw us deſtroyed one after another. And at laſt bore up and let fall his main Sail, and fired a Gun to Lee-ward, to call off all his Fleet, which was done, and away they went with nine Sail, and were chaſed but with eight Sail of the Dutch. All this time the <hi>Leopard</hi> had her Colours flying, but they ſeeing no hopes of any Relief, were forced to yield up their ſhip, being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powered by the enemy. All this I ſhall be ready to witneſs upon Oath, whenſoever I ſhall be called thereunto. And to conclude, if Captain <hi>Badily</hi> had been a Pentioner to the Sates of <hi>Holland,</hi> he he could not have done them better Service.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:170623:10"/>
               <p>I <hi>William Ell</hi> have peruſed this Narration, concerning the Fight he was in at <hi>Linorno</hi> with the Dutch the Fourth of <hi>March,</hi> 1652. and do teſtifie, and ſhall be ready to make good upon Oath, that this is truth which is here ſpecified.</p>
               <p>Firſt, That ſoon after Captain <hi>Appleton</hi> was clear of the <hi>Mould-head</hi> with his Squadron, the wind Southwards, and the Dutch tacked upon them, and that then all Captain <hi>Badily</hi>'s Squadron might have come to them.</p>
               <p>Secondly, As ſoon as we came to know the Ships, after the blowing up of the <hi>Bonaventure,</hi> and that fierce Encounter, We found two great Ships of the Enemies on board of the lar-board ſide of the <hi>Leopard,</hi> and all three lay driving with their Heads of to the Weſt-ward.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Sampſon</hi> aſtern and to lee-ward of them in a flame, and the <hi>Levant</hi> Merchant boarded by another great Ship of the Holland<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. Now Captain <hi>Badily</hi> and all of his Squadron was to wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of them, and of all the Enemies Fleet, and ſhot, as Captain <hi>Appleton</hi> ſaith, but at to great a diſtance, but ſome went nearer; and for my own part, being Commander of the <hi>Lewis,</hi> I went within Piſtol-ſhot of the <hi>Leopard,</hi> and ſpent ſeveral Broad-ſides on thoſe Ships that lay on Board her, and on others, and was reſolved to be on Board thoſe two Ships to relieve the <hi>Leopard;</hi> but the firſt time going up to her, the <hi>Conſtant Warwick</hi> puts us aſtays, ſo was forced to tack, and we tacked twice to recover the wind again of the <hi>Leopard</hi> to get aboard of her (or them) to relieve her, and brought all our beſt Guns over on that ſide that bore of them, and double ſhotted them for that purpoſe; and though I had one mans head ſhot off, and another ſhot through the back (from ſide to ſide) with great ſhot, and ſeveral men wounded, yet were the reſt deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to go aboard to relieve our Vice-Admiral: But Captain <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diley</hi> ſeeing me lean to lee-ward, he being on the other tack with his Ships head to the Weſt-ward, bore towards me, and called to me to tack and ſtand away after him; ſo finding my ſelf the lee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardmoſt Ship of that Squadron, and ſeeing they were not inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to Engage, I tacked and ſtood after them.</p>
               <p>Concerning Captain <hi>Whiting</hi> in the Fire-ſhip, he kept near to Captain <hi>Badiley,</hi> and at our firſt coming up, after theſe ſad acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, Captain <hi>Badiley</hi> and he was the weathermoſt Ships; and then likewiſe was the Dutch Admiral ſingled out, and to the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therward (which was occaſioned by loſs of her Stearidge, having her Rudder ſhot, as I heard) I thought then Captain <hi>Badiley</hi> would taken the opportunity and engaged him, or at leaſt led up the Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to him, but the Fire-ſhip went alone, and ere could come up with the Dutch Admiral, he ſunk her.</p>
               <p>We had the wind at S. S. E. or thereabouts, when Captain <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diley</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:170623:10"/> with the reſt of his Squadron, with the <hi>Mary,</hi> which made nine in number, ſtood away, there was eight of the Dutch ſtood after us till night; we all went better then they, and had the wind of them, yet durſt we not face them though none of us had very great damage, my ſelf the moſt, yet wiſhed we had tacked upon them after they were come to Sea (for the reſt of their Fleet, as the wind was, would not have gotten out of Port after them) if we had but tacked, I believe they would have ſtood back again, which would have given a good wipe, though not a clean one to our Cowardizm.</p>
               <p>For what was done after we ran away, I can ſay no more, but that I ſee ſeveral of the ſaid Dutch Ships that ſtaid in Port paſs their Broad-ſides into the <hi>Leopard,</hi> that I thought it not poſſible for any man in her to maintain a Quarter, yet I ſee her fire ſeveral times, and to my judgement kept up her Flag about four hours af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter we began to run.</p>
               <p>The wind continued at S. S. E. all that day, and our Admiral kept cloſe upon a wind, and kept ahead, ſo that we could not with all our Sail get up that night to ſpeak with him: This I have col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected out of my own Journal, and am ready to juſtifie it to be truth,</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Witneſs my hand.</dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>I <hi>Benjamin Fiſher,</hi> was deſired to declare the truth of what I was an eye-witneſs concerning our Engagement at <hi>Legorn</hi> the fourth of <hi>March,</hi> 1652.</p>
               <p>Firſt, That Captain <hi>Richard Badily</hi> ſent that very Morning we ſet Sail out the <hi>Mould,</hi> to Captain <hi>Henry Appleton</hi> not to come forth the <hi>Mould</hi> in caſe the Dutch weighed not; for Word was brought from Captain <hi>Badily,</hi> That he did intend to ſtand in fair aboard the <hi>Lanthorn</hi> by Morning, and ſalute the Town.</p>
               <p>Secondly, That Captain <hi>Richard Badily</hi> ſent in two Meſſengers after that to haſten our coming out, though expreſly commanded by the former Meſſenger from Captain <hi>Badily</hi> not to budge; whereupon ſeeing that he was ſo wavering in his Reſolution, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptain <hi>Appleton,</hi> with the reſt of the other Commanders, did argue upon it not to Sail, but to follow his firſt Order, which was to lie ſtill in caſe the Dutch weighed not; which ſaid Dutch lay in a half Moon, within Muſquet ſhot of the <hi>Mould-head,</hi> with their Top<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſail-ſheets hal'd home, and their Fore-ſails of the moſt part of them was in the Brails.</p>
               <p>But we expecting to ſee Captain <hi>Badily</hi> flet fair by the <hi>Lanthorn,</hi> when day came on, they were as far diſtant from us as they were over night; for by their own Squadrons relation, they lay mouſel four Glaſſes, which if they had not, they might have very well been
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170623:11"/> in with the ſhore by morning; and by the help of the Almighty, they might have been a means to ſav'd our Squadron, and no doubt we had worſted the Dutch Boats. In the morning the Dutch weighed, and as ſoon as they were to the South-ward of the <hi>Mould,</hi> there was no time neglected in getting out, according to Captain <hi>Badily</hi>'s Order. But we were no ſooner clear of the <hi>Mould</hi>-head, but the Dutch tackt and ſtood with us, and by that ſudden accident which befel the <hi>Bonaventure,</hi> ſeparated our Squadron; for ſome of us was forced to bear to Lee-ward, and ſome kept to Windward, and for my own part, went with our ſhip through part of the wrack, and within ſhort ſpace after, the Wind South-ward on us; but what with the ſmoke of our own Guns and the Enemies, I could not diſcern one ſhip hardly from the other; but ſtanding through the Dutch Fleet, having diſcharged divers broad-ſides at the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, I came within a Cable-length of Captain <hi>Badily,</hi> and bore away thwart his fore-foot, and brought our ſhip to the other tack, and went firing into the Fleet before him, and paſt our broad-ſide at the two ſhips that was aboard the <hi>Leopard</hi> on her Larboard-ſide, and ſuppoſing Captain <hi>Badily</hi> to have ſtood along to the relief of our Squadron; when we had paſt the Enemy, that we were got to the Northward of them, ſo that there was none fired at us, we ſaw Captain <hi>Badily</hi> ſtanding away with all ſail he could make, top<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galant-ſail and all, we put our ſhip aſtays, having much ado to get her about, by reaſon all our Braces, and Bolens, and Sheets, and Tacks were ſhot; when we had got our ſhip about, we let her fall off round, and fired our broad-ſide at the two ſhips that was aboard the <hi>Leopard,</hi> and then we ſet our main-ſail and all the ſail we could, for Captain <hi>Badily</hi> was got ſome half a League from us, with the reſt of his Squadron following him. The <hi>Leopard</hi> all this while firing at the two ſhips that was aboard her, and at others that paſt by her. We were the Lee-ward-moſt ſhip of all and the Norther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, yet we had never leſs then five Fathom water; we had nine ſail of the Dutch following us, yet our Ambral never ſo much as did ſhorten ſail for any of our Fleet that was aſtern, the which made me think he had been kill'd, he leaving the <hi>Leopard,</hi> and the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant,</hi> and the <hi>Peregrine</hi> in that ſad condition: But my opinion is, that if Captain <hi>Badily</hi> with all our nine ſail had ſtood in once more, we had ſaved the <hi>Leopard,</hi> if not the <hi>Levant,</hi> and had gone near to have chaſed ſome of the Dutch aſhore; for all Captain <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily</hi>'s Squadron had little damage, for we might have ſtood in, had Captain <hi>Badily</hi> been ſo minded, and reſcued Captain <hi>Appleton,</hi> for he was not taken a large hour after we left him in diſtreſs; for as far as we could diſcern, we could ſee his Flag flying, and after we could not diſcern the Flag, we could hear the Guns go off very faſt. Our Ambral all this time never ſhortned ſail whereby we might come to ſpeak with him till the Monday, following, to declare to him how
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170623:11"/> our ſhip was torn. And what I have here declared, is nothing but the Truth, and ſhall make Oath, if call'd to it.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Benjamin Fiſher.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A Relation of Signior</hi> Montemagni, <hi>one of the Secretaries of State to the Great Duke of</hi> Toſcany, <hi>concerning his Negotia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion between the Engliſh and the Dutch, upon the re-taking of the</hi> Phenix <hi>Frigot.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>UPon my arrival at <hi>Legorn,</hi> I did with all the earneſtneſs I could, endeavor to perſwade Signior <hi>Van Gale<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> the Dutch Admiral, to be contented with that Anſwer the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> had ſent his Highneſs, which was, That Captain <hi>Appleton</hi> was ſent for home, to give account thereof. But finding that this would not do, I asked him what kinde of Satisfaction he would pretend unto; he anſwered, He did expect the reſtitution of the Frigot, or elſe in ſtead of that, that all the Engliſh Veſſels in the <hi>Mould</hi> ſhould reſign their Rudders and their Sails. At laſt, after a long diſpute, he ſaid it ſhould ſuffice, if two of their men of War ſhould reſign their Rudders and their Sails into his Highneſs hand, until the <hi>Phenix</hi> was reſtored unto them; although the Difference was great be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the value of the Veſſel at that time they took her, and the condition ſhe ſhould be in when ſhe were returned.</p>
               <p>Hereupon I acquainted Captain <hi>Badily</hi> with what had paſt, laying before him the neceſſity of finding out ſome way for to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt this buſineſs; but it was all in vain, for he denied to yield to any thing, ſaying, That rather then he would yield the leaſt unto his His Highneſs or the Dutch, in caſe he might have time to fit himſelf, he would go out to Sea with all his Fleet. After my ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving waited for a better Anſwer, giving him time to think the bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the conſequences of ſuch a Reſolution, I told him, in caſe he would deliver one of his Ships into my Maſters hand, I would endeavor that ſhould paſs for ſatisfaction: but this he ſleight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed too.</p>
               <p>At laſt I told him, if he would give it under his hand, that he would return the Frigot, that that ſhould paſs for ſatisfaction, and that his Highneſs would continue ſtill his beſt Protection to him. But ſuch was the perverſeneſs and obſtinacy of Captain <hi>Badily,</hi> that he not onely refuſed to hearken to any of thoſe reaſonable moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but in ſtead thereof, writes a Letter to his Highneſs, the Copy whereof followeth; wherein he declares, That he will no longer bear any reſpect unto his Highneſs Port, but will fall upon his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies where he findes them.</p>
               <p>His Highneſs perceiving that the ſervices he had lately done Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptain <hi>Badily</hi> were forgot, and that the further need he might have
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170623:12"/> of him was not at all conſidered, and ſeeing he would neither ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept any propoſitions made to him, nor make any himſelf whereby his Highneſs might give any colour of Anſwer to the Dutch; but that in ſtead thereof declareth, That he is ſo far from giving ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for the former wrong done to his Highneſs, that he proteſts he will commit new ones; My Maſter commanded me to let him know, that ſeeing none of the forementioned means will be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of, and foraſmuch as it was Captain <hi>Badily</hi>'s own propoſition that he might go out of his Port, that he would give him twelve days time to fit himſelf for his departure, though he again deſired him rather to think of ſtaying.</p>
               <p>This Captain <hi>Badily</hi> aſſented to, and notwithſtanding that he had revoked his promiſe not to diſturb the Port, ſaying, He would aſſault the Dutch; nevertheleſs his Highneſs continued his prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to him, commanding that the Dutch ſhould not aſſault the Engliſh.</p>
               <p>Upon this I acquainted <hi>Van Galen</hi> with Captain <hi>Badily</hi>'s Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, but found him unwilling to accept thoſe tearms, ſome of his biggeſt ſhips being then away, and news being brought of ſome ſupplies that were coming to the Engliſh; but then I told him his Highneſs neither could do more, nor was it reaſon that they ſhould expect it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Van Galen</hi> then demanded to know the time preciſely when the Engliſh would depart; but as I had commiſſion from my Maſter, I then told, That to reveal the ſecrets of one Enemy unto another, would manifeſtly be derogatory to his Highneſs honor. Being of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended at this Anſwer, <hi>Van Galen</hi> ſendeth his Vice-Admiral and three other Captains to me, to proteſt, That ſince they might not know what time the Engliſh would depart, they would omit no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſetting on them in the <hi>Mould.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His Highneſs being incenſed at this their raſhneſs, commanded that the Conſul, Captains and Sea-men of the Dutch that were aſhore, ſhould all be ſeized upon, the which accordingly was done to the number of ſeven Captains, and one hundred Sea-men; withal, commanding the Governor of <hi>Legorn</hi> to conſult with the Engliſh the beſt way for their ſecurity. In the mean time Captain <hi>Badily</hi> writes a ſecond Letter to his Highneſs, which with its An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer follows, wherein his Highneſs gives him longer time, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes yet more in caſe he ſhould require it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Van Galen</hi> ſeeing the Duke reſolved to protect the Engliſh, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to bear reſpect unto his Port, whereupon the Duke under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that the Engliſh had ſet ſayl from <hi>Porto Ferara,</hi> he relea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Dutch; and ſeeing all the means he uſed to reconcile them was without effect, according to Captain <hi>Badily</hi>'s requeſt, he gave them leave to try it out at Sea.</p>
               <p>The Engliſh departed four days before their time expired, and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170623:12"/> might have had what longer time they would; whence it is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed that Captain <hi>Badily</hi> going out to fight by his own election, not at all compelled, did think he had advantage over his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and ſurely ſo he had, if the Battel had been better managed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To the Great Duke of <hi>Toſcany.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>May it pleaſe your Highneſs,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>SInce you are pleaſed to honor me with a Credential Letter of the 18 curant, four days ſince I received the ſame by the hands of the highly deſerving and much honored Perſon, the Secretary of State, who informed me of what your Highneſs did demand, and to whom I gave an Anſwer ſo modeſt and humble, that I hope it will be ſatisfactory. Amongſt other Commands the Councel of State, eſtabliſht by the Authority of the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> ordered me, as for the reſpect, which as I ſhould however have born to your Highneſs, ſo upon other conſiderations alſo, that I ſhould in no maner aſſail the Dutch in your Highneſs Port, except they firſt aſſailed the Engliſh, the which according to my duty I have ſtill obeyed; But ſince the Dutch do carry no reſpect unto your Highneſs, but lord it over every Nation, chaſing not onely others, but alſo your Highneſſes Subjects veſſels at the <hi>Mould</hi> head,</p>
               <p>I therefore humbly releaſe my ſelf of that Engagement, which I formerly had made unto your Highneſs, hoping you will not take it ill, if I take the ſame advantage againſt the Dutch as they do againſt the Engliſh; ſo wiſhing your Highneſs all ſplendor and felicity, I ſubſcribe my ſelf,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your Highneſs humble Servant,</hi> RICH: BADILY.</signed> 
                  <dateline>From <hi>Legorn</hi> 
                     <date>14 of <hi>February,</hi> 1653.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>To his Highneſs the Great Duke of</hi> FLORENCE.</head>
               <p>ON Saturday laſt I received thoſe lines with which your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was pleaſed to honor me, bearing date the 28 of the laſt Moneth, and although that I deſired with all my heart, that this Diſpute about the <hi>Phenix</hi> Frigot might be finiſhed at this Treaty; nevertheleſs having recovered the ſaid Veſſel by ſo notable a ſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagem, I reſt not any way ſatisfied how I can anſwer it to them that employ me, if I ſhould deprive my ſelf voluntarily of her again, or of any other Veſſel in her place. And laſtly, when I ſhall
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170623:13"/> intend your Highneſs will about that time limited for my going out, I ſhall immediately apply my ſelf to comply therewith, and that moſt joyfully, hoping it will ſo ſucceed: I onely beg, that in caſe our Veſſels are not gone out of the <hi>Mould</hi> at <hi>Legorn</hi> before the laſt day, and that the Wind ſhould be contrary, this ſhould be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted (as really it is) a juſt Impediment; I onely fear, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we cannot ſtay one day in the Road for the providing of Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſt without being moleſted, leſt that ſome of out Veſſels ſhould periſh in caſe that any ſtrong Wind ſhould ariſe before the Diſpute were ended. Your Highneſs pleaſeth alſo to remember, that ſince by my former Letter, I releaſed my ſelf of my Engagement which I had firſt made concerning the Hollanders and their confederates, I aſſure your Highneſs upon my honor, that this was occaſioned by the Inſolency of our Enemies, to the end that when they knew it, they might reſt mortified and in ſome meaſure humbled, and conſequently reduced by the Treaty, to accept that which ſhould be judged reaſonable; becauſe, being there was no other means probable to prevail, I did believe that by this they would be ſeized upon with ſome fear, thinking that we were provided with a greater ſtrength then they knew of.</p>
               <p>I was always of opinion, That if a body entred into another mans houſe to refreſh himſelf, although a private perſon, he ſhould carry himſelf humbly, and much more in the Chamber of a Prince; and therfore, according to the commands I have received from my lords &amp; maſters in engliſh, I ſhall render your Highneſs all due reſpect, and ſhall not moleſt his Ports, particularly the Road of <hi>Legorn,</hi> while the Hollanders ſhall do the ſame. And ſuppoſing all within the <hi>Malory</hi> to be the Port and Chamber of your Highneſs, ſo neither ſhall I directly nor indirectly moleſt the Enemies of our Nation, or any that belong to them; and moreover, neither my ſelf nor any under me, ſhall weigh Anchor to chaſe any one coming in or going out, and ſhall be obedient to any juſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands your Highneſs ſhall give us, as well in our going away with all our Fleet within three or four days more or leſs, or to any other elſe: And I really believe, that the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> will order the ſame reſpect to your Highneſs from all others that ſhall ſucceed me in theſe parts, to the end the moſt floriſhing trade of <hi>Legorn,</hi> which hath been eminent for ſo many years, ſhould not meet with any impediment from the Engliſh.</p>
               <p>The Dutch now will not give the ſame reſpect, becauſe they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve themſelves ſtrong enough to ruine us; but indeed they may be deceived for all that: we have eight Men of War in this place and <hi>Port Langone,</hi> and ſix in <hi>Legorn,</hi> which is not much diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable to the ſtrength which they had yeſterday in <hi>Legorn:</hi> and if your Highneſt ſhall pleaſe to ſend once more another Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger to the Dutch Admiral, to know if they will render to his
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170623:13"/> Highneſs Port the ſame reſpect was promiſed by the Engliſh, to give them encouragement for the better encouragement of the Dutch: and to the end your Highneſs ſhould be no longer troubled with us, I have made certain Propoſitions which ſhall be by me punctually obſerved, as alſo, all that is contained in this Letter; and for the Execution hereof, I believe that Mr. <hi>Longland</hi> the Publique Miniſter of the Commonwealth of <hi>England,</hi> will oblige himſelf, together with me, as on the other ſide I do deſire that <hi>Vander Straten</hi> will oblige himſelf, together with <hi>Van Galen,</hi> in the preſence of ſome Publique Miniſter of your Highneſs: So leaving all this to the Conſideration and Diſcretion of your Highneſs, I ſay no more.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your Highneſs humble Servant,</hi> RICH: BADILY.</signed> 
                  <dateline>From <hi>Porta Feraro</hi> 
                     <date>the 6 of <hi>March,</hi> 1653.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The PROPOSITIONS.</head>
               <p n="1">I. IF the Dutch Admiral will oblige himſelf, That without being moleſted I ſhall come into the Road of <hi>Legorn</hi> with my eight ſhips and Fly-boat which are here, and ſhall within forty eight hours be ready to ſet ſayl, and that we may ſtay without fighting till the other ſhips can come out of the <hi>Mould</hi> and provide themſelves with Ballaſt, then on the other ſide will I oblige my ſelf not to moleſt the Dutch while they are there, and that I will go without the <hi>Malora</hi> when he ſhall appoint, and being without the <hi>Malora,</hi> I ſhall there freely wait until his ſhips ſhall come within Muſquet ſhot, there to diſpute it fighting like men, and not to moleſt and diſhonor the Port of that Prince, who hath refreſhed both of us with the fruit of his Countrey.</p>
               <p n="2">II. Having underſtood that the Dutch the other day brag'd, That they would fight with the Engliſh ſeven to ſeven: to the end they ſhould not make this Objection, I ſay, That I ſhall grant them for every ſeven ſhips of ours, one, ſo that if we are fourteen in number, they ſhall be ſixteen: And to the end they ſhould not ſay, that our Veſſels are bigger then theirs, I ſhall give them, when I make a Liſt of the men, in every ſeven one.</p>
               <p n="3">III. When the Fight ſhall be over, in caſe the Engliſh prove Conquerors, and return into the Road with all their Fleet, and there finde four or five Merchant-men, or perhaps ſome of their Men of War, which may be ſoundly torn, I do promiſe not to ſhoot or fight with them within the <hi>Malora,</hi> provided the Dutch will do the ſame with us.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>RICHARD BADILY.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:170623:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Great Dukes Anſwer to Captain</hi> Badily, March 9. 1653.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>IT being agreed upon at the Treaty concerning the departure of the Squadron out of <hi>Legorn,</hi> the deſire I have to ſerve the Commonwealth of <hi>England,</hi> induceth me to gratifie your Requeſt, in the prolonging of the term of the departure until the Eighteenth Currant; and in caſe you cannot conveniently depart, I ſhall be very ready for to grant you further time; as to the Challenge which you ſend the Dutch, it is a buſineſs which concerns me not: I approve well of the reſpect you promiſe to my Port, and queſtion not the Hollanders will do the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Captain</hi> Appletons <hi>Letter to the Councel of State.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Right Honorable,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THe ſecond inſtant, the Colonel of this Town by the great Dukes Order, ſent Mr. <hi>Longland</hi> and the Conſul to acquaint me with theſe Propoſitions the Dutch had made him; <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That no Man of War, having an opportunity to depart, ought by a moſt ancient Law to ſtay in any Port beyond ſuch a time.</p>
               <p>That they, to that end the Engliſh might go to ſea, had ſtaid out ſeveral days.</p>
               <p>That they would give the Merchants Ships leave to relade their Goods, give them free liberty to depart, nor would they ſtir till they had departed five days.</p>
               <p>In caſe theſe Propoſitions were refuſed, they could not juſtifie their not acting their Commands they had received touching the the Engliſh, in whatſoever place they met them.</p>
               <p>To theſe I was immediatly to give my Anſwer: The general Opinion of the Nation then preſent was, That whereas the Dutch had waited ſeveral times upon the Duke, and did ſolicit daily that he would deny protection to the Engliſh; and all this while the Engliſh never owned him, nor went to give him thanks (as I indeed had ordered it, but Mr. <hi>Longland</hi> oppoſed me in it:) The Duke now ſeemed to ſpoil the vertue of our gratitude, by his neceſſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting us unto it: So Mr. <hi>Longland</hi> did deſire me before the Nation, to ſend one to treat with the Duke accordingly, That himſelf, with other Merchants, would go to thank him for the protection of their Goods, and that the Maſters would do the ſame for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of their Ships, and joyntly to beſeech him the continuance of his favor.</p>
               <p>Hereupon my ſelf, and many others, earneſtly deſired Mr. <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanael Reading</hi> to undertake that buſineſs on my behalf, the which he pleaſed to do; with what diſcretion he managed the whole bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170623:14"/> with how great acceptation to his Highneſs, your Honors will underſtand from his publique Miniſter with you.</p>
               <p>With what ſucceſs to us, your Honors may pleaſe to judge of by his effecting the continuance of our protection; the Particulars whereof, are in his own incloſed to you.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Legorn,</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>Auguſt</hi> 8. 1653.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Nathanael Readings <hi>Letter to the Councel of State.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Right Honorable,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>UPon ſeveral Solicitations that in Captain <hi>Appletons</hi> name I ſhould wait upon the great Duke, in anſwer to the Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons the Dutch had made him the third inſtant, in company with Mr. <hi>Charls Longland,</hi> Mr. <hi>Samuel Boneil,</hi> and the Captains of the <hi>Sampſon, Mary</hi> and <hi>Perigrine,</hi> I ſet out for <hi>Florence,</hi> and through Gods aſſiſtance came thither the fourth at Evening; ſo ſoon as we arrived, I acquainted them how that the Duke had ſent three times to ſee if we were come, that it concerned us therefore quickly to conſider the quality of the Perſonage that we came to, and of the buſineſs that we came about: To this end, I deſired Mr. <hi>Longland</hi> what his errand was, he told me, It was to thank his Highneſs, in the name of the Merchants, for the protection of their Goods: I demanded if he came as Agent for the State, he told me, Not, that he had no Commiſſion for ſuch Imployment, and that the Duke well knew, that beſide, his education had not been to underſtand how to treat with Princes: That he knew not how to ſpeak unto a Duke, and therefore did deſire Mr. <hi>Boneil,</hi> who had been with him often, to do it for him; asking the Captains then what they came for, they ſaid, to thank him for the protecting of their Ships; here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon I ſhewed them my Commiſſion from Captain <hi>Appleton,</hi> and becauſe I had to joyn, as I then thought, with ſuch States-men, and ſo earneſtly deſired the buſineſs might be carried handſomly, told them what I would ſay unto the Duke, asking withal their Judgement, if they did think of any thing to adde or alter, and I ſhould hear them readily: They ſaying it was very well, departed, each of us fitting of himſelf for Court: Mr. <hi>Longland,</hi> while al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering his clothes changed his minde, and when the Meſſenger came for us, told me, That Captain <hi>Appleton</hi> had no power to ſend un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Duke, that he would proteſt againſt him there, and write againſt him unto your Honors, although he was the perſon that firſt deſired him to ſend. With all the meekneſs man could uſe, I did beſeech him by the affection which he had for the Honor of the State of <hi>England;</hi> I did conjure him to remember what he was about, that as to his power over Captain <hi>Appleton,</hi> he would
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170623:15"/> diſpute it afterwards, and for the preſent, what notion ſoever he would act in, I ſhould not diſturb him, but that when he and every body elſe had done, I might be heard for Captain <hi>Appleton;</hi> he told me poſitively, he would neither own nor joyn with me in any thing concerned him; ſo carrying the other company along with him, he goes to the Court.</p>
               <p>Hereupon, I acquainted Sir <hi>Bernard Gaſcone</hi> with the Buſineſs I came on, and what had paſſed betwixt Mr. <hi>Longland</hi> and my ſelf; that I would wait till he had Audience, and ſee what Anſwer he could give the Duke, when he demanded where he was that Captain <hi>Appleton</hi> had ſent, for ſo his Secretary had adviſed him by the accompt the Conſul of <hi>Legorn</hi> had given him of our co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming. After that they had made an end, his Highneſs asked them whether Captain <hi>Appleton</hi> had not ſent a Gentleman unto him in Anſwer of thoſe Propoſitions he adviſed the Colonel of <hi>Legorn</hi> to acquaint him with? Mr. <hi>Longland</hi> anſwered, There was no ſuch perſon come: ſo he diſmiſſed them. So ſoon as they were gone, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately Sir <hi>Bernard</hi> goes in, and tells the Duke, how that I was without, ſhews my Commiſſion, and brings me to his Highneſs, to whom as followeth;</p>
               <p>That Captain <hi>Appleton</hi> humbly kiſſed his Highneſs hand, in the acknowledgement of thoſe Favors he had been pleaſed to ſhew him; the which, according to his duty, he ſhould have done both earlier and oftner, but that he waited he might have from his Maſters hand, to whom he had ſent on purpoſe to enform them of the ſame.</p>
               <p>That at his coming out, he was commanded by the States of <hi>England</hi> to attend the ſecurity of their Ships from the Piracies of the French, and them to convoy to all the Ports that they were bound to touch at.</p>
               <p>That upon that accompt he came into <hi>Legorn,</hi> and ſince his being there, the Dutch forgetting thoſe good Offices they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived at the hands of <hi>England,</hi> and inſolently committing ſeveral things tending to the violation of its Peace, he had received Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders from the State to ſtay in <hi>Legorn</hi> till their further pleaſure.</p>
               <p>That upon any apprehenſion of Violence from the ungrateful Dutch, in caſe he were not able to defend himſelf, he ſhould make uſe of his Maſters Intereſt for his Protection, the which they did aſſure themſelves would be ſufficient, his Highneſs being ſo very careful of his Port, and willingly granted, he being ſo courteous a Prince, and no leſs careful of his friends.</p>
               <p>That upon the Threats of Fourteen ſails of Dutch that came into the Road, he was by the Commanders of the Port deſired to come into the <hi>Mould,</hi> not having promiſe of Protection while without: his men of War being but two, and the Merchants ſhips ſo conſiderably rich, he embraced their counſel.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:170623:15"/>
               <p> As to the Enemies Plea, That no man of War, by a moſt anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Law, ſhould ſtay in any Port beyond ſuch a time; they have as little Logick in their Argument, as they have Wiſdom in beginning War with their beſt friends. For neither the <hi>Rhodian</hi> Law, the firſt that ever were obſerved in the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> Sea, the which the <hi>Romans</hi> with their Empire did enlarge, and every of the Ports therein, upon the ruine of that Empire did admit. Nor yet the Rule of <hi>Oleron,</hi> by which the Ocean was originally, and is this day governed, in any way deny the ſame; beſides, themſelves remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber well, and of neceſſity muſt grant, we know a multitude of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Preſidents to the contrary.</p>
               <p>As to the re-lading of the Goods, and their offer to remain be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde, till the Engliſh were five days out at Sea, he would not capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulate with them for his departure, but humbly beſeeched his Highneſs leave to ſtay, not daring to ſtir without their Order who put him there.</p>
               <p>And laſtly, as to the Hoſtility they ſo much threatned, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Engliſh ſuffers in his Highneſs Port, the State would ſtrickly require at his Highneſs hands; but that I was well aſſured he was ſo noble and ſo wiſe a Prince, as that he would not give any occaſion to diſtaſte the Engliſh, or ſo undervalute them, as to put the Friendſhip of <hi>Holland</hi> in competition with that of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His Highneſs vvas pleaſed to tell me, That he highly honored the State of <hi>England;</hi> that he deſired nothing more then a fair Correſpondence with them: That he reſted abundantly ſatisfied in the Account I had given him on Captain <hi>Appleton</hi>'s behalf, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring me to reſt fully ſatisfied on his, That if all the Forces in his Dominions could protect the Engliſh, it ſhould be done, and that ſo long as they ſhould need the ſame.</p>
               <p>He then demanded why Mr. <hi>Longland</hi> ſhould tell him ſo groſs a lie, being it was his motion I ſhould come, and that he came in company with me, and brought himſelf that Letter which betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, ſaying, He was not uſed to be ſo dealt withal. I humbly told him, that what reaſon Mr, <hi>Longland</hi> had, his Highneſs would beſt know from himſelf, but that for my part, I knew none he had; ſo ſending for him preſently, he prayed me to return in the morning. Accordingly I came, and then he pleaſed to tell me, that Mr. <hi>Longland</hi> pretended a Commiſſion beyond Captain <hi>Appleton</hi>'s, but that he was perſwaded there was no ſuch matter. I humbly beſeeched his leave for my departure, adding, That what his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs vvas pleaſed to require further, I vvas there ready to obey him in: He anſwered, That he knew I could not ſtir in the heats, but that he would not fail to diſpatch me that night, and that he would give order for the Gates to be open, and Horſes to be ready for me.</p>
               <p>Coming at night, his Highneſs told me, how that he did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170623:16"/> that Captain <hi>Appleton</hi> ſhould bear all fair reſpect unto his Port, without diſturbance to the Trade. I then engaged my Parole unto him, That the Comportment of the Engliſh to his Highneſs ſhould always be like themſelves; but that in caſe the Dutch likewiſe ſhould not obſerve the ſame, it could not be ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed we ſhould be civil to our prejudice, nor that other of our Commanders, though Captain <hi>Appleton</hi> ſhould, would not take the ſame advantage againſt the Dutch.</p>
               <p>I then deſired his Highneſs Order, That the Colonel of <hi>Legorn</hi> ſhould uſe ſome extraordinary care, fearing the ſick condition that Captain <hi>Appleton</hi> was in might animate the Dutch in their at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts againſt him; he preſently commands his Secretary to write accordingly, and told me, how Sir <hi>Bernard</hi> had informed him of my being a Slave to the <hi>Turk;</hi> and therefore while the Letter was in writing, pray'd me, to give himſelf and his brother <hi>Cardinal,</hi> whom he then ſent for, an accompt of <hi>Candy,</hi> of the laſt years fight at Sea, of the diſcipline of the <hi>Turks,</hi> and the maner of the Captain <hi>Baſha</hi>'s uſage of me, which he underſtood was extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary; I obeyed his commands in each.</p>
               <p>His Secretary having done, his Highneſs read the Letter to me, asking me, if it were to my minde, commands him to give me a Copy of the ſame: I in all humility returning many thanks for his Civilities to our Nation, and promiſing to let their Honors know, the care he took for the Protection of your Ships, and my endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voring to perpetuate that Amity which hath ſo long continued be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt his Highneſs and our Nation; I kiſſed his Hand, and ſo took leave.</p>
               <p>At my arrival at <hi>Legorn.</hi> I found the Colonel punctual in the performance of what the Letter did command him, and ready up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all occaſions to ſerve the Engliſh.</p>
               <p>This is the ſhorteſt accompt I could give your Honors of the Endeavors I had to ſerve you, wherein, if you can conceive I have done any thing for which to beg your pardon, be pleaſed, that the reality of the Soul I acted in, may obtain it from you.</p>
               <p>Thus praying the Lord of Hoſts to be your Champion, and him that is the Wiſdom of his Father to be your Councellor, I humbly commit you to his Protection.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Great Dukes Reſident his Letter to the Councel of State.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Right Honorable,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>HAving on Thurſday laſt forgotten to tell your Honors, That when I firſt acquainted the laſt Right Honorable Councel of State of the Engagement that Admiral <hi>Appleton</hi> had made to the Great Duke of <hi>Tuſcany</hi> my Maſter not to moleſt his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170623:16"/> Port of <hi>Legorn</hi> directly or indirectly; I ſhould (by his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment) have alſo added, how Mr. <hi>Nath: Reading</hi> waited then on the Great Duke ſeveral times about that Buſineſs, and did then engage his Parole for Captain <hi>Appleton,</hi> that he ſhould punctually obſerve the Orders he received from the Right Honorable, the Councel of <hi>England,</hi> not to diſturb any maner of way his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs Port of <hi>Legorn.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Mr. <hi>Reading</hi> being now in <hi>London,</hi> can give your Honors full relation of each particular until ſurpriſal of the <hi>Phenix.</hi> Thus much, I ſay, I was commanded by my Maſter to enform the ſaid Councel of State, as I do now your Honors, That the ſaid Mr. <hi>Reading</hi> did manage that whole Negotiation with ſuch a diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that his Highneſs was exceedingly pleaſed at him, and did judge him a perſon very capable to do his Countrey much good ſervice. I humbly intreat your Honors to accept now, what then I forgot, to participate unto your Honors from his Highneſs, and me, for</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your Honors moſt obliged and moſt devout Servant,</hi> Amerigo Salvetty.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>June</hi> 11. 1653.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
               <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
